<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Leadership on James Bowman</title>
    <link>http://www.jamesbowman.me/tags/leadership/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Leadership on James Bowman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <copyright>Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY)</copyright>
    <atom:link href="http://www.jamesbowman.me/tags/leadership/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Socratic questions revisited [infographic]</title>
      <link>http://www.jamesbowman.me/post/socratic-questions-revisited/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Feb 2017 21:46:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.jamesbowman.me/post/socratic-questions-revisited/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;A little over a year ago, I wrote a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jamesbowman.me/post/socratic-questions/&#34;&gt;blog post examining Socratic Questions&lt;/a&gt;. Socratic Questions are a method of pull influencing that can be used to stimulate critical thinking.  To help make the question types easier to understand and remember for use in practice, I have gone back and created an infographic illustrating the 6 types of questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The infographic is shown below (click on the infographic for the full size version).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jamesbowman.me/post/socratic-questions-infographic.pdf&#34;&gt;
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.jamesbowman.me/post/socratic-questions-infographic.png&#34; alt=&#34;Infographic illustrating the 6 types of Socratic Question&#34; /&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Please share any experiences in the comments below, or if there are particular types of questions you find useful to aid critical thinking that are not included.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;R. W. Paul, L. Elder: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/The-Thinkers-Guide-Socratic-Questioning/dp/0944583318&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Thinkers Guide to The Art of Socratic Questioning, 2007&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Socratic questions</title>
      <link>http://www.jamesbowman.me/post/socratic-questions/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Aug 2015 16:51:47 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.jamesbowman.me/post/socratic-questions/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;In my last &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jamesbowman.me/post/leadership-styles/&#34;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt;, I looked at situational leadership and how different influencing styles and techniques can be effective in different contexts with people at different levels of maturity.  &amp;lsquo;Push&amp;rsquo; (directive) influencing techniques are more focused on &amp;ldquo;telling&amp;rdquo; whereas &amp;lsquo;Pull&amp;rsquo; (non-directive) techniques tend to involve the use of questions and reflection to guide.  One particular technique involving the use of questions to influence in this way is &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Socratic_questioning&#34;&gt;Socratic questioning&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Socratic_questioning&#34;&gt;Socratic questioning&lt;/a&gt; is a practice adapted from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Socratic_method&#34;&gt;Socratic method&lt;/a&gt; to stimulate critical thinking.  It involves systematic questioning to explore ideas, critically analyse logic and consider broader perspectives.  It is frequently used in education and psychological therapy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like other &amp;lsquo;Pull&amp;rsquo; influencing techniques, Socratic questions and the Socratic method can be particularly effective when trying to overcome resistence or resolve differences of opinion.  This is because the technique helps the individual to critically examine the logic of their own argument and is highly effective at highlighting any flaws or inconsistencies in that logic in a non-confrontational way.  This is especially useful when dealing with people suffering from &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Illusory_superiority&#34;&gt;illusory superiority&lt;/a&gt; (the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dunning%E2%80%93Kruger_effect&#34;&gt;Dunning-Kruger effect&lt;/a&gt;) as it can help them consider broader perspectives and identify their own lack of knowledge.  Since Socrates believed the first step to knowledge was recognition of one&amp;rsquo;s own ignorance it follows that his method focuses not so much on proving your point but on helping the other person recognise the flaws in theirs.&lt;/p&gt;










&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;bloglogo&#34; href=&#34;#&#34; onclick=&#34;window.open(&#39;https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=%27Socrates+believed+the+first+step+to+knowledge+was+recognition+of+one%27s+own+ignorance%27+-+http%3A%2F%2Fwww.jamesbowman.me%2Fpost%2Fsocratic-questions%2F%3Futm_source%3Dtwitter.com%26utm_campaign%3Dclicktotweet%26utm_medium%3Dsocial+by+%40jamesebowman&#39;, &#39;_blank&#39;, &#39;width=500,height=350&#39;); return false;&#34; style=&#34;text-decoration:none;&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Socrates believed the first step to knowledge was recognition of one&amp;#39;s own ignorance&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;color:#00aced;&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;icon-twitter&#34; style=&#34;font-size:1.5em;&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; Tweet this&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;



&lt;p&gt;There are essentially 6 types of Socratic questions (based upon those proposed by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/The-Thinkers-Guide-Socratic-Questioning/dp/0944583318&#34;&gt;R. W. Paul&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;1-clarifying-thinking-and-understanding&#34;&gt;1. Clarifying thinking and understanding&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can you give me an example? &lt;br&gt;
Could you explain further? &lt;br&gt;
Are you saying X? &lt;br&gt;
What is the problem you are trying to solve? &lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;2-challenging-assumptions&#34;&gt;2. Challenging assumptions&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is that always the case? &lt;br&gt;
Are you assuming X? &lt;br&gt;
Do you agree that X? &lt;br&gt;
If that is true for one X, is it true for all X? &lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;3-examining-evidence-and-rationale&#34;&gt;3. Examining evidence and rationale&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why do you say that? &lt;br&gt;
How do you know? &lt;br&gt;
What data is there to support this?
Why? &lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;4-considering-alternative-viewpoints-and-perspectives&#34;&gt;4. Considering alternative viewpoints and perspectives&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are there any alternatives? &lt;br&gt;
What is the other side of the argument? &lt;br&gt;
What makes your point of view better? &lt;br&gt;
What would X say about this? &lt;br&gt;
Can you think of any cases where that is not true? &lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;5-considering-implications-and-consequences&#34;&gt;5. Considering implications and consequences&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What would be the implication? &lt;br&gt;
Are there any side effects?  &lt;br&gt;
What if you are wrong? &lt;br&gt;
How can we find out? &lt;br&gt;
If this is true, does it mean X is also true? &lt;br&gt;
What else should we be considering? &lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;6-meta-questions&#34;&gt;6. Meta questions&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why do you think I asked that question? &lt;br&gt;
What does that mean? &lt;br&gt;
What else might I ask? &lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;R. W. Paul, L. Elder: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/The-Thinkers-Guide-Socratic-Questioning/dp/0944583318&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Thinkers Guide to The Art of Socratic Questioning, 2007&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Leadership styles</title>
      <link>http://www.jamesbowman.me/post/leadership-styles/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jul 2015 06:39:34 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.jamesbowman.me/post/leadership-styles/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Traditionally people used to think leadership was an inherent quality and that individuals have their own distinct leadership style.  In practice, each style has its own strengths and weaknesses, situations where it excels and others where it is less effective.  Therefore, whilst it is natural to have a preferred style that one feels most comfortable with, a good leader should be able to adapt their style depending upon the situation or context, the team or individual being influenced and the task at hand.  This is called &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Situational_leadership_theory&#34;&gt;Situational Leadership&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Situational_leadership_theory&#34;&gt;Situational Leadership&lt;/a&gt; is a theory of leadership and influencing developed by &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paul_Hersey&#34;&gt;Paul Hersey&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ken_Blanchard&#34;&gt;Ken Blanchard&lt;/a&gt;.  The theory assumes that an individual or team&amp;rsquo;s maturity is an evolutionary progression from low to high.  When individuals approach a task or activity for the first time, they have very little knowledge or skill but these develop over time with education, practice and experience.  As an individual or team&amp;rsquo;s maturity increases, they respond better to less directive influence from a leader or coach and conversely, people with low maturity in a given task respond better to more directive influencing styles.&lt;/p&gt;










&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;bloglogo&#34; href=&#34;#&#34; onclick=&#34;window.open(&#39;https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=%27As+an+individual+or+team%27s+maturity+increases%2C+they+respond+better+to+less+directive+influence%27+-+http%3A%2F%2Fwww.jamesbowman.me%2Fpost%2Fleadership-styles%2F%3Futm_source%3Dtwitter.com%26utm_campaign%3Dclicktotweet%26utm_medium%3Dsocial+by+%40jamesebowman&#39;, &#39;_blank&#39;, &#39;width=500,height=350&#39;); return false;&#34; style=&#34;text-decoration:none;&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an individual or team&amp;#39;s maturity increases, they respond better to less directive influence&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;color:#00aced;&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;icon-twitter&#34; style=&#34;font-size:1.5em;&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; Tweet this&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;



&lt;p&gt;The idea of maturity as an evolutionary progression is not uncommon and is central to &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maturity_model&#34;&gt;maturity models&lt;/a&gt; and popular models in learning theory such as the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Four_stages_of_competence&#34;&gt;four stages of competence&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dreyfus_model_of_skill_acquisition&#34;&gt;Dreyfus Model of Skill Acquisition&lt;/a&gt;.  Like &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Situational_leadership_theory&#34;&gt;Situational Leadership&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dreyfus_model_of_skill_acquisition&#34;&gt;Dreyfus Model&lt;/a&gt; also supports the idea that different influencing and teaching styles are more effective with teams or individuals at different stages of maturity.  For example, &amp;lsquo;Novices&amp;rsquo; (the lowest level of maturity in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dreyfus_model_of_skill_acquisition&#34;&gt;Dreyfus Model&lt;/a&gt;) require close supervision and respond well to clear rules and check-lists to follow, but as they progress towards &amp;lsquo;Experts&amp;rsquo; (the highest level of maturity) they become increasingly self-sufficient and typically respond better to non-directive input.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;directive-and-non-directive-styles&#34;&gt;Directive and non-directive styles&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leadership and teaching styles can be broadly categorised into two types: directive and non-directive.  With directive styles, the leader is typically the person who defines the solution and then tells the team or individual what to do.  With non-directive styles, the leader helps the team or individual arrive at the solution themselves usually by asking guiding questions.  Directive and non-directive styles are often referred to as &amp;ldquo;Push&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Pull&amp;rdquo; respectively to reflect the nature of the influence and where the solution is coming from.  The diagram below is based upon one by &lt;a href=&#34;http://mylesdowney.com/&#34;&gt;Myles Downey&lt;/a&gt; and shows a spectrum of coaching skills and how they are typically associated with push or pull styles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jamesbowman.me/post/CoachingSpectrum.jpg&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.jamesbowman.me/post/CoachingSpectrum.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;A spectrum of coaching skills supporting Push (directive) to pull (non-directive) influencing styles&#34; class=&#34;pure-img&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;sup&gt;&lt;sub&gt;image: based upon &lt;a href=&#34;https://books.google.co.uk/books/about/Effective_Coaching.html?id=zifwAAAAMAAJ&#34;&gt;Myles Downey&amp;rsquo;s Spectrum of Coaching Skills&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This diagram shows that a leader can choose different techniques and adapt their style to be more or less directive.  &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Situational_leadership_theory&#34;&gt;Situational Leadership&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dreyfus_model_of_skill_acquisition&#34;&gt;Dreyfus Model&lt;/a&gt; demonstrate that different techniques tend to be more effective with people at different levels of maturity but there are other reasons a leader or coach might choose certain influencing techniques over others.  &amp;ldquo;Push&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Pull&amp;rdquo; techniques can yield very different outcomes.  For example, &amp;ldquo;Push&amp;rdquo; techniques can be effective in achieving compliance and yielding fast results where as &amp;ldquo;Pull&amp;rdquo; techniques tend to take much longer but can be more &amp;ldquo;sticky&amp;rdquo;, achieving lasting commitment and behavioural change, empowering people to solve problems themselves and making them more self-sufficient for the future.  Pull techniques also tend to be more effective in persuasion and overcoming resistence and can be used to help stimulate critical thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>